[MUSIC]
Ok, hello everyone welcome to the
Programming Languages class.
I 'm Dan Grossman and I'm looking forward
to having a great class with all of you.
And what i want to do is sort of natural,
and this sort of first lecture is
just give you an overview of what the
class is going to sort of be like.
And get you excited about what we're
going to do.
And basically over the next 10 weeks, I
hope that
we will, together, learn the fundamental
concepts underneath programming languages.
So, I don't intend for this to be an easy
course.
But I think it's something that with hard
work, and patience,
and coming in with an open mind ready to
learn new things.
it has the opportunity to make everyone a
better programmer than they came in before
the course.
And in fact I think it will make you a
better programmer in programming languages
we're not going to study at all.
And even in programming languages you
already know.
So the idea is that we're going to learn
the concepts that come up in any
programming language.
And get better at recognizing them
despite the surface level differences
between languages.
So what tends to happen all the time when
people look at a course like this.
Is they say, oh, that's the course that
teaches ML, Racket, and Ruby.
Which are the three programming languages
we're going to use.
But I really don't like that description
of the course.
because the idea is that we're just going
to use those languages
as vehicles to learn the concepts that
come up in any programming language.
In any case, this video is not going to
cover programming languages at all.
It's going to be more of the course
mechanics, that sort of stuff.
Then the next one I'll do a little more of
course introduction
that's programming-language specific and
then we'll
get going into the course content.
Here's a real simple list of things you
can do right now,
even before you get started on the first
homework and things like that.
the obvious thing to do is get familiar
with the course website.
How the different pieces are laid out.
if you have taken a Coursera course
before, I think it'll be fairly familiar.
But we all do things a little bit
differently.
And if not, I don't think you'll have too
much trouble.
But take a few minutes.
Look at the different sections.
Get started on the discussion board, that
sort of thing.
Second, I hope you'll complete the
beginning
of course survey, I think that'll be fun,
so that we can all find out more about the
community that we're all participating in.
And it shouldn't take you any time.
And third, and this is probably the most
time-consuming and important,
get the software installed that you need
for the first homework.
We're going to be using an editor and a
programming language and
a couple of tools that you may not be
familiar with.
And it's a bit of a pain to get it all
installed.
We've provided step by step instructions
that you can just read through.
We've also provided some videos of me
literally installing the same software
on Windows which may be helpful.
And this is just stuff that you may was
well do now.
That is you wait until you're ready to
start the homework.
You'll just find it more aggravating.
So it's a good thing to do early maybe
after even just
watching this first video or the second
one or something like that.
give you a brief overview of the sort of
materials
that'll be available to you as you go
through the course.
Obviously there will be lectures like
this.
I also have written reading notes covering
all the same material.
So you don't need to read these because
they'll by
and large cover the same material that we
cover here interactively.
With slides and writing code and with me
talking.
but they can be really helpful if you want
a more
precise explanation, or you just like to
read a few sentences to
get exactly the point I'm trying to make.
And so I really encourage you to read
those, and
will always post those together with the
other lecture materials.
any code that I, show or write, or we go
through in one of
the lectures, I'll post separately so that
you can actually have the text file.
Rather than having to retype it or paste
it out of a PowerPoint slide.
I will have homework assignments.
Those homework assignments are going to
get graded both by scripts
we've written.
That are going to read through and, you
know, run them
against tests and give you points and that
sort of thing.
And we're also going to use some very
simple pure assessment.
Meaning that you are going to have your
assignment graded by a few
other students in the class, and you are
going to grade a few.
This is going to be very simple.
It's going to be something like a rate on
a one through five sort of thing.
And this helps me emphasize that it's not
enough to just pass the test.
What we're trying to do is learn how to
write software
in clean, elegant, beautiful ways.
And that's something that humans can
evaluate much better than computers.
Also have a couple exams.
one about halfway through, and one at the
end.
And that's because there's a number of
concepts in this course
that I want you guys to learn and answer
questions about.
that you can't really demonstrate your
knowledge of by just writing programs.
So most of the homework will pretty much
be all programming, and then the exams
will
ask some more other conceptual questions.
in terms of the homework, we'll probably
have seven, so
there won't be one for every week of the
course.
And I'll keep you apprised of how that is
working out.
You should do them individually although
of course you'll get help
on the discussion board and from fellow
students as you need.
And the thing I always like to emphasize
is, is if
you want to do them efficiently and learn
the most from them.
the counter productive way to do it
is just try to get the right answer and
crank out
the code as quickly as you can and turn it
in.
usually, you'll actually find it takes
less time.
If, when you approach a homework question.
You look at hey, what concept is this
question
related to that we went through in the
lectures?
Then write the code that pretty much has
it working.
And then to make sure you got it, test
your code.
And, even try some variations.
Say well, I think this
is right, but if I change this around a
little bit,
I'd bet it's wrong, and here's the test
it's going to fail.
And I think if you do that, you'll get a
lot more out of
the homework, and you'll be much more
confident that you have the right
solutions.
Just this one more logistically or
structural things, sometimes on
the homework, I'll have what I call
challenge problems those
are just somewhat more difficult problems
that those of you
who find the course a little bit easier
might enjoy doing.
And that you can learn a lot more from.
But for the rest of you, you don't have to
do them.
We'll make them worth just a small number
of points so that
people who do them feel they get something
tangible out of it.
but you are welcome to skip them, so you
can think of them as optional.
Last sort of thing about the homeworks.
I've sort of learned from experience, that
students are sometimes
surprised at how precisely and concisely
my homework questions are worded.
I think that's because I'm a computer
scientist, and
I tend to write English the way I write
code.
Which is I put exactly what needs to
be there and make sure it's defined very
precisely.
And I think for technical questions like a
homework problem that's the great
way to do it.
but what this means is that if you're use
to sort of standard internet
work where you just skim things and try to
get the high level idea.
You might find them very frustrating.
So I encourage you when you get into
especially the first homework assignment.
I've really try to trust that each word
and
phrase there and each question is there
for a reason.
Read it all the way through.
I've try to keep them as short as
possible.
Just a couple of pages
long usually.
and I think you'll find them a lot easier
to
approach if you take a sort of no skimming
allowed view.
Now that doesn't mean that the homework
will always be crystal-clear to you.
So, if you are confused, that's what the
discussion board is for.
I may have even made a mistake, although I
certainly don't intend to.
And, what typically happens, is you think
a
homework question is very confusing in how
it's worded.
But then after you do it, if you go
back and read the question again.
you'll see, oh that's not confusing at all
maybe I was the one that was confused.
and that's how you learn the material, and
I'm
looking forward to exploring that process
with all of you.
a few other things that we'll do in the
class
I'll try to put on the web page everything
you need.
But when your're learning new programming
languages, learning new
ideas, you sometimes have to look up
details elsewhere.
I won't do that on purpose.
But you also
shouldn't be surprised if you find
yourself looking up some
language feature that's not covered in the
lecture or something.
I, and occasionally I'll have some
optional material, some offshoots where
I'll say here's a little video that if
know say C programming.
you might appreciate this connection with
something you already know.
there's a small group of TAs that are
mostly
behind the scenes, but we'll see how the
course goes.
And maybe they'll do some, video question
answering or something so that they can
have some of the fun tool.
And the bottom line is I just hope this is
a great adventure for all of us.
you know I hope to really create an
active, energetic community.
I hope to share with you My passion and my
excitement for programming
languages is my favorite class in the
world, which is maybe not too surprising.
That that's the one I chose to create for
this Coursera environment.
And I actually have a now not so secret
goal, which is.
It's well known for these classes that
only a small percentage of students
who start the course stick with it all the
way through and finish it.
And, and I hope we set records for that.
I'm not going to make the class easy.
I hope it's challenging because that's
what
I think will actually keep you engaged.
But I would really love for people to look
at this community we're creating ten
weeks from now and say, wow, that was,
that was one of the best ones.
How did they do it I, I, I hope more
courses are like
that and let's see if we can work together
to make that happen.
Okay.
So at this point you are welcome to stop
watching this video.
I've covered what I need to cover for the
course.
But I thought if your going to spend all
these
hours over the next couple months
listening to me.
you might like to know a little bit more
about me.
Just like I would be very curious to learn
a little bit more about you.
At least from filling out the online
survey so I can get some aggregate
information.
So this is just for fun
if your curious.
This is my country, this is the United
States, I grew up
right in the middle of it until I was 18
years old.
I lived in the suburbs of St. Louis,
Missouri.
After that, I went off to college in
Houston, Texas.
I loved going to Rice University.
I really miss the burritos, that's
probably
my favorite thing about living in Texas.
After that I went and got a PhD at Cornell
University in Ithica, New York.
It's a small town.
If you're not familiar with New York
State,
that's a 4 and a half hour drive from New
York City.
So it's actually a small town.
quite a distance from the larger cities.
And then in 2003, I moved to Seattle.
Which is the, my favorite place that I've
ever lived in.
And I've been a faculty member at the
University of Washington since then.
A little bit about my research and
teaching and what
I do, I do consider myself a programming
languages person.
But a bit of an applied one, or a little
bit of a strange one.
Where what
I like to do is take the fundamental
beauty of programming languages.
Things like the functional languages and
type systems
that we're actually going to study in this
course.
And instead of necessarily working to make
them better, I try
to take the ideas behind them and apply
them to other areas.
Areas where you might not expect them to
be as applicable.
So I have worked a lot over the last
few years in trying to make multi-threaded
programming.uh, easier.
So that it's, you can more effectively and
efficiently program,
the multicore chips that are becoming
ubiquitus in the computing industry.
I'm now working a bit on how you can
better write software that' s more
energy efficient so batteries last longer
and
you spend less money on your power bill.
I've worked on other things a bit, like
web programming
or, dealing with programs that process
massive amounts of data.
And this
is really just like the, the way I like to
operate.
That I like to collaborate with others
that maybe
don't have as much of a programming
languages background.
And then I learn from them some of the
real world needs that they have.
And, and somehow we, we combine to, to
make
progress and, and to make computing and
software better.
outside of that, I don't spend all my
time sitting inside recording videos and
doing research.
I love to go hiking, this is a picture of
me from
up in Montana last summer.
About once a week, I go and play ice
hockey.
You can't tell this is me at all, but that
actually
is me under the gear there in the front of
the picture.
I love riding my bike, this is me
finishing up a 200 mile
or 320 kilometer bike ride from Seattle to
Portland, a couple summers ago.
And if that's not enough sort of cute, fun
pictures.
this is the dog I live with, and her name
is Red Dog and she's amazingly awesome.
Okay I also like to travel.
Here's a list of countries I visited,
ranked in order from smallest to largest.
So I'll be curious to see if we have
students
in class from most or possibly even all of
these countries.
I also traveled all over the United
States.
I am missing three states, I'm still
hoping to get to Alaska Delaware and
Hawaii.
So, welcome.
That's a little bit about me.
Remember to tell me a little bit about
you.
And in the next video, we'll get started
on programming languages.